A Guide to the Papers of the Twin Oaks Community,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 1: Councils
  - K. Planning Council
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Goal and Values survey proposals, 1979; 1982, 34 items. (Box-folder 39:8)
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Goals and Values survey proposals, 1982; n.d., 24 items. (Box-folder 40:1)
      Notes on options that the planners didn't choose; notes on food and dining; notes on minority living space proposals; sample questionnaire to find out what members want in their residence; notes about the privileges for visitors; notes for survey questions; Report on Yossi Amir's Visit and a Summary of Ideas about a Comprehensive Planning Project.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Planners notes, 1979-1980; n.d., 64 items. (Box-folder 40:2)
      Taylor's notes for decisions made on social planning.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Process Beginning, 1979, 9 items. (Box-folder 40:3)
      Summary of getting started; Publication Social Planning, A Small Group Problem; opinion and idea paper on the subject of design preference values survey; opinion and idea paper on small groups; book report on The Oregon Experiment; information on a comprehensive planning project.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Process Creation, 1979, 50 items. (Box-folder 40:4)
      Social planning proposal; social planning meeting notes; notes and designs from the small group study committee; summary of public process section; notes on definition process; history of the process. OS Step-by-step plans and notes.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Process Evaluation, 1979, 3 items. (Box-folder 40:5)
      List of tools and surveys used in the planning process.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Process. Matrices, n.d., 70 items. (Box-folder 40:6)
      Reference sheet for methods; values and goal matrices. OS Matrices.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning Process. Methods, n.d., 16 items. (Box-folder 40:7)
      Methods summary; miscellaneous method analyses; method analysis of child care; method analysis for decision making and labor; method analysis for membership and visitors; reference sheets for methods; methods for activities exercise. OS Papers on social methods.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Residence, 1979, 14 items. (Box-folder 40:8)
      Social Planning proposal; notes for survey questions.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Small living groups meetings, 1980, 14 items. (Box-folder 40:9)
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Small living groups surveys, 1979-1980; n.d., 32 items. (Box-folder 40:10)
      Surveys on small living group rights and responsibilities; living space questions; new tupelo questionnaire; Small group and child directions survey.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Small living groups surveys, n.d., 19 items. (Box-folder 41:1)
      Small group and child directions survey.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Small living groups surveys, n.d., 15 items. (Box-folder 41:2)
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Space and functional Relationships, n.d., 47 items. (Box-folder 41:3)
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Surveys. Growth Re-visioning, 1981, 16 items. (Box-folder 41:4)
      Growth re-visioning surveys completed by members.
    - Planning Council. Social Planning. Surveys. Growth Re-visioning, 1981, 17 items. (Box-folder 42:1)
  - L. Support Council
    - Support Council. Archives. Communication, 1982-1989, 16 items. (Box-folder 42:2)
      Request to move communications center; request for more considerate responses on the opinion and idea space and 3 x 5 boards; discussion of norms for using the opinion and idea space; opinion and idea papers about norms and the bluster board.
    - Support Council. Archives. Oaken Flooglehorn, 1988-1990, 25 items. (Box-folder 42:3)
      Flooglehorn, the community newsletter which gives updates and schedules of events.
    - Support Council. Archives. Office, 1975-1989, 20 items. (Box-folder 42:4)
      List of councils; planner notes; priority request for an archivist position and office space; archives budget worksheet; plan-writing worksheet; list of planner decisions; proposal to eliminate the Support Council due to the lack of common interests between councils; laminated miscellaneous signs [for notebooks].
    - Support Council. Archives. Opinion and idea paper Indexes, 1982-1993, 29 items. (Box-folder 42:5)
      List of opinion and idea papers organized by year; report showing the number of opinion and idea papers written by members; summary of outstanding opinion and idea papers; idea of a ghost writer for members who don't like to write opinion and idea papers.
    - Support Council. Archives. Process Team, 1986-1989, 19 items. (Box-folder 42:6)
      A history of the 'process' of communicating and implementing policy; Opinion and idea papers on 'process' and the Process Team; guidelines for membership feedback; sign up sheet for facilitation training; dialog meeting notes; Planner's meeting notes; Conflicts with the Visitor Managers, members, and the Process Team; letters to the process team; Process Team reports and job descriptions.
    - Support Council. Holidays, 1981-1989, 56 items. (Box-folder 42:7)
      Holiday menus, invitations; schedule, notes, reunion weekend brochure; anniversaries; discussion about celebrating Thanksgiving; Summer, Fall and Winter Solstices; Budget Planwriting worksheet.
    - Support Council. Library, 1987-1989, 5 items. (Box-folder 42:8)
      Fine policy, budget worksheet; design for a newspaper magazine rack; survey; information about newspaper subscriptions.
    - Support Council. Movement Support. Anti-War, 1985; 1989, 3 items. (Box-folder 42:9)
      Membership proposal for escrow account; member letter on war registers league; flyer for meeting.
    - Support Council. Movement Support. Freedom House, 1988-1989, 8 items. (Box-folder 42:10)
      Information on members volunteering at the Freedom House, a homeless shelter in Richmond; list of volunteers; thank you notes from Freedom House.
    - Support Council. Movement Support. Politics, 1981-1987, 37 items. (Box-folder 42:11)
      Prayers of the Fascists by Roque Dalton Garcia; request for labor credits for activism; proposal for bumper stickers; information about Peace Walk, World Peace March, and Solidarity Rally; information about hurricane aid; letters to the editor; thank you letters; discussion about individual vs. community support for politics; periodical subscriptions; endorsement of political candidates; conference on feminism; opinion and idea papers and meeting notes on Uranium mining.
    - Support Council. Movement Support. Politics, 1983-1985; 1987-1989, 36 items. (Box-folder 42:12)
      Budget plan-writing worksheet; Opinion and idea papers on movement support and politics; Louisa County Senior Center; Habitat for Humanity Walk; news clipping about the Charlottesville Peace Center; news clipping about the Adopt a Highway program; an article titled, Peace and the World Economy by [Rosurthian;] list of donations to organizations and various causes.
    - Support Council. Movement Support. Politics. Nuclear power and waste, 1978-1988, 26 items. (Box-folder 43:1)
      History of nuclear wastes at North Anna; letters by members; letter from the NZ government about their anti-nuclear policies; clippings on North Anna; member proposal for a nuclear free zone; meeting notes of planner's forum; planner notes/discussion notes on proposal; printed letter from President Ronald Reagan to Twin Oaks.
    - Support Council. Movement Support. Refugees, 1986-1987, 20 items. (Box-folder 43:2)
      Refugee report; newsletters from Central American Refugee Center; correspondence with Overground Railroad, Reba Place Church, First Unitarian Church of Richmond, Charlottesville Refugee Assistance Friends Meeting House, and Proyecto Libertad about refugees; proposals to host legal refugees; meeting notes; information about loans from the Unitarian Universalist fellowship.
    - Support Council. Movement Support. Refugee family, 1987-1989, 63 items. (Box-folder 43:3)
      Information on provisional legal refugees (PLR); request forms for asylum in the US; Information on Jesus and Adela, refugees they hosted in the community temporarily; copy of immigration bond records; invoice for hospital check up; floppy disk.
    - Support Council. Recreation, 1977-1987, 34 items. (Box-folder 43:4)
      Identification of specific recreational uses of land; discussion about noise in the courtyard; proposal for Mardi Gras; invitations to dances, parties; dance policies; proposal for events; talent show program, spring play programs; communal use of raft; volleyball; basketball; hiking, camping, canoeing; choral group; drama circle; spiritual places; information on a tape recorder; film projector; information on computer sharing, and dark room for photography; Four point game; trips. OS Flyers for events.
    - Support Council. Recreation. Music, 1985-1989, 8 items. (Box-folder 43:5)
      List of recordings; information about a CD player in the Hammock shop; opinion and idea paper on donating records in Llano to the Goodwill; songs, concert announcements; information about music collections; programs, reviews on music performances; opinion and idea paper about theater; play programs; letter and notes on plays and performances.
    - Support Council. Recreation. Parties, 1981-1991, 26 items. (Box-folder 43:6)
      Flyers for birthday and special occasion parties.
    - Support Council. Recreation. Video, 1982-1991, 41 items. (Box-folder 43:7)
      Video reviews; request for videos; notes about movie discussion; Opinion and idea paper; meeting agenda on video violence; record of videos shown; video budget worksheet; notes on video games.
    - Support Council. Recycling, 1987-1989, 4 items. (Box-folder 43:8)
      Proposal, discussion notes on dumpsters and dump runners; opinion and idea papers on metal resources.
    - Support Council. Social Groupings, 1988, 6 items. (Box-folder 43:9)
      Opinion and idea paper about groups of five; guidelines and notes about selection of groupings; list of groups.
    - Support Council. Weeds & Knots, 1987, 16 items. (Box-folder 43:10)
      Notes and opinion and idea paper on Twin Oak newsletter, Weeds & Knots; meeting notes; records.
  - M. Transportation and Maintenance Council
    - Transportation and Maintenance Council. Auto Maintenance, 1982-1989, 20 items. (Box-folder 44:1)
      Policy for borrowing tools; report to the Planners about a conflict between members of the auto team; The AutoMaint Inquirer; The Autohead Enquirer; Vehicle Maintenance Report; proposal for upgrade and repairs on vehicles; Planwriting worksheet; opinion and idea papers about hurtful comments, a new member, new van, investment of body work, new Toyota, and job openings; opinion and idea paper on manual or auto transmission; Planwriting worksheet; guidelines on vehicle use.
    - Transportation and Maintenance Council. Bicycles, 1981-1989, 5 items. (Box-folder 44:2)
      Community bike policy and availability of bikes; planwriting worksheet; request for cart.
    - Transportation and Maintenance Council. Roads, 1984-1989, 4 items. (Box-folder 44:3)
      Opinion and idea paper on moving Llano road, speed bumps and snow removal.
    - Transportation and Maintenance Council. Travel, 1980-1984, 7 items. (Box-folder 44:4)
      Opinion and idea papers proposing reimbursement for mileage, hiring a ride service, and buying a small car; recommendations for long trips.
    - Transportation and Maintenance Council. Vehicle issues, 1985-1989, 8 items. (Box-folder 44:5)
      Use of personal cars and community regulations; vehicle ownership meeting; opinion and idea papers on vehicle ownership.
    - Transportation and Maintenance Council. Vehicle Use, 1989-1995, 29 items. (Box-folder 44:6)
      Mileage and cost charge and other vehicle usage policies; proposal to eliminate chargebacks; proposal to revise vehicle use rates; opinion and idea papers about increasing the number of vehicles; request to keep trailer at Modern Times temporarily; opinion and idea paper about car accidents and safety; discussion notes on changing the by-laws to include personal cars for members.
    - Transportation and Maintenance Council. Vehicle Use, 1983-1988, 29 items. (Box-folder 45:1)
- Series II. Controversial Issues
  - Controversial Issues. Air Conditioning, 1987-1989, 21 items. (Box-folder 45:2)
    Opinion and idea papers, priority request; proposals to implement AC in the community; meeting notes.
  - Controversial Issues. New Dairy Barn, 1983-1989 August, 26 items. (Box-folder 45:3)
    Letters and papers involving a conflict between members concerning continued use of the current Dairy Barn or building a new barn; description of a new dairy barn; Dairy Plan Committee notes to the Planners; New Dairy Facilities Proposal; overview of the Dairy Barn decision process.
  - Controversial Issues. New Dairy Barn, 1989 September-November, 16 items. (Box-folder 45:4)
    Planner Forum meeting notes; analysis of the Dairy Barn decision process and an opinion and idea paper on an appeal process.
  - Controversial Issues. Farm, 1979-1980, 10 items. (Box-folder 45:5)
    Decision is made by Planners to discontinue farming due to high turnover in membership at Twin Oaks and difficult conditions for farming to be profitable; opinion and idea papers about the decision. OS Notes on controversial farming.
  - Controversial Issues. Gender, 1979-1987, 12 items. (Box-folder 45:6)
    Invitation for men's nurturance night; letter to planners requesting that they consider more women for managerial roles; debates about excluding men from a showing of a Lesbian erotica film, censorship of songs with offensive lyrics to women, gender only parties; Opinion and idea papers on gender and work assignments, on egalitarian consciousness and work; an article titled Girl Talk, by John Pfeiffer. OS Paper on male visitors.
  - Controversial Issues. Gender, 1988, 10 items. (Box-folder 45:7)
    Opinion and idea papers on Female Culture Dominance at Twin Oaks Community by Zena Goldenberg, Revolution, How Do Men Fit into Feminist Culture, and a paper on Values and Choices by the process team.
  - Controversial Issues. Interpersonal, 1984-1985, 6 items. (Box-folder 45:8)
    Letters between members who are in conflict with each other, opinion and idea paper that shows concern that the community is separating.
  - Controversial Issues. Morale, 1978-1986, 24 items. (Box-folder 45:9)
    Opinion and idea papers on many aspects of living at Twin Oaks, quotas for hammock production, values and idealism; responses to other members; notes on members spanking children; pet peeves about language and space issues. OS Paper about norms at Twin Oaks by Novagene.
  - Controversial Issues. Morale, 1977-1978; 1987-1989, 13 items. (Box-folder 46:1)
    Opinion and idea papers on earning quotas in one area while competence for another area is unused, leadership, understanding change in community, and a debate about boycotting business with certain companies for political reasons; Report of a meeting about members violating an agreement involving television viewing.
  - Controversial Issues. Noise, 1981-1988, 9 items. (Box-folder 46:2)
    Opinion and idea papers on noise at late-night parties at the Llano Building, hammock shop, and loud-music.
  - Controversial Issues. Nudity and Shirtlessness, 1987-1988 March, 10 items. (Box-folder 46:3)
    Request by a Twin Oaks teenager to invite a guest to the New Year's Eve party but it is refused due to a consensus of the members desiring to have nudity; opinion and idea papers about the request and the issue of nudity in the community; pledge sheet agreeing to protocol regarding nudity; discussion about the rights of children at Twin Oaks.
  - Controversial Issues. Nudity and Shirtlessness, 1988 April-1989, 26 items. (Box-folder 46:4)
    Discussion about sending children to public schools where they will be influenced by mainstream values or educating them in the community where conflicts about nudity will be less likely to occur; opinion and idea papers about nudity policy, and appeals to change the policy.
  - Controversial Issues. Smoking, 1978-1979, 4 items. (Box-folder 46:5)
    Meeting notes, procedures and opinion and idea papers on smoking in the community.
  - Controversial Issues. Thefts & Vandalism, 1978-1987, 8 items. (Box-folder 46:6)
    Vandalism on property at Twin Oaks; news clipping about a robbery by a Twin Oaks member; opinion and idea papers on building construction, and about a lost wallet; apology letter from a former member with a habit of stealing; vandalism of fuel system, and other acts of vandalism; letter by a member about pursuing life as an activist outside of Twin Oaks.
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Correspondence. Community, 1975-1976; n.d., 23 items. (Box-folder 46:7)
    Correspondence between members.
  - Correspondence. Community, 1978-1989, 30 items. (Box-folder 46:8)
    Opinion and idea papers; correspondence between members.
  - Correspondence. Contacts with Academic Institutions, 1986-1989, 35 items. (Box-folder 46:9)
    Academians request literature and visits to Twin Oaks; letter of request for information about Twin Oaks; academic contacts questionnaire; invoices; directory of Utopian scholars.
  - Correspondence. Ingrid Komar about Living the Dream, 1979-1987, 38 items. (Box-folder 46:10)
    Ingrid (Ma-Bear) proposes writing a book about Twin Oaks; tentative outline, book agreement; correspondence of Twin Oaks concerning the content/progress of the book; correspondence of Twin Oaks over a dispute of the preface written for the paperback; information about Ingrid's son. OS Correspondence regarding Living the Dream.
  - Correspondence. Members and former members, 1977-1984, 77 items. (Box-folder 46:11)
  - Correspondence. Members and former members, 1985-1987, 60 items. (Box-folder 47:1)
  - Correspondence. Members and former members, 1988-1991, 51 items. (Box-folder 47:2)
  - Correspondence. Members and former members, n.d., 35 items. (Box-folder 47:3)
  - Correspondence. Other, n.d., 27 items. (Box-folder 47:4)
  - Correspondence. Travel, 1981-1989, 19 items. (Box-folder 47:5)
  - Correspondence. Visitor, 1970-1987; n.d., 56 items. (Box-folder 47:6)
  - Correspondence. Visitor, 1977-1989, 26 items. (Box-folder 47:7)
  - Correspondence. Visitor, 1976; 1978, 7 items. (Box-folder 47:8)
  - Correspondence. Writers request information about Twin Oaks, n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 47:9)
    Correspondence of media/publisher concerning using Twin Oaks in books/articles; letter from Chuck Farrier thanking Twin Oaks for allowing him to write a book.
- Series IV: Culture
  - Culture. Achievements, 1975-1988, 11 items. (Box-folder 47:10)
  - Culture. Artwork, n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 47:11)
    Pencil sketch; drawings.
  - Culture. Books and resources, 1972; n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 47:11)
    Bibliography for many subjects such as sociology, education, history, feminism, economics, children and management; suggestions for readings in leadership, power and equality.
  - Culture. Children, 1982-1985; n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 47:12)
    Dance sign up sheet; short stories and poems by children.
  - Culture. Groups & Classes, 1981; 1985-1989, 16 items. (Box-folder 47:13)
    Men's group meeting information; sign language classes; counseling classes.
  - Culture. Humor, 1983-1987, 20 items. (Box-folder 47:14)
    Invitations; agenda for international convention of knee injury survivors; request for hammock prices; opinion & idea paper on wanting to live at Twin Oaks; information about life outside the community.
  - Culture. Marriages, 1983-1984, 4 items. (Box-folder 47:15)
    Invitations and thank you notes for weddings.
  - Culture. Menus, n.d., 78 items. (Box-folder 48:1)
    Menus for meals on special occasions. OS Menus.
  - Culture. Names, 1983-1987; n.d., 10 items. (Box-folder 48:2)
    Ideas for names of buildings and cars.
  - Culture. Nature, 1982-1988, 9 items. (Box-folder 48:3)
    Listing of birds and wildlife seen at Twin Oaks; information on a total eclipse; hiking trip; flower viewing.
  - Culture. Newsletter titled Acorn, 1987-1989, 12 items. (Box-folder 48:4)
    Spring 87 issue of Acorn (a newsletter about arts at Twin Oaks) and notes.
  - Culture. Papers appreciating Twin Oaks, 1978-1989, 93 items. (Box-folder 48:5)
    Opinion and idea (I like it) papers where members make notes about their favorite things at Twin Oaks. OS Magazine articles including Town & Country.
  - Culture. [Publications] Articles about Twin Oaks, 1967-2003, 31 items. (Box-folder 48:6)
    OS News clippings.
  - Culture. [Publications] Discussion about purchase of Kat Kinkade's A Walden Two Experiment, 1983, 1 item. (Box-folder 48:7)
  - Culture. [Publications], n.d., 12 items. (Box-folder 48:8)
  - Culture. Spirituality, 1976; 1987, 3 items. (Box-folder 48:9)
    Proposal to purchase spiritual books and materials; information on new metaphysical books; information on meditation.
  - Culture. Surveys, 1984; 1988; n.d., 8 items. (Box-folder 48:10)
    Surveys on bathroom; survey on 1 day plague; survey on how many members are left-handed; survey on how members like their eggs.
  - Culture. Women, Feminism and Lesbianism, 1979-1988, 17 items. (Box-folder 48:11)
    Correspondence from editors of women's newsletters; Twin Oaks correspondents requesting advertising for women interested in alternative lifestyles; application for change in space use for Oneida to become a women's space; notes from a meeting about sexism; updated memo about small living groups; opinion and idea papers on Wimmin Power, From the Womyn's Group to You, Men's space, 'Wolfing,' 'Word Awareness,' Egalitarian Consciousness and Work.
  - Culture. Women, Feminism, and Lesbianism, n.d., 11 items. (Box-folder 48:12)
    Opinion and idea papers on Values and Choices; request for Oneida to become a women's space; a paper about Living In Community; women's meeting notes; news clipping; advertisement for Oakyn-wymny; planning on a community center relocation; articles about being Lesbian.
  - Culture. Work and Rest, 1974; 1987-1990; n.d., 10 items. (Box-folder 48:13)
    Essay about thinking of work in terms of creativity; flyer requesting help for 70 hour work weeks; proposal for a day-off; request support for a member who struggles with reaching enough hours to meet quota; once a week event with various special events notes, menu, discussion notes on Community Day.
  - Culture. Writings, 1980-1985; n.d., 14 items. (Box-folder 48:14)
    Poems and songs written by members; Political Science paper by A. Allen Butcher, titled Democracy and Capitalism; 'group story' where each reader adds more narrative to the story. OS Writing titled, A story for the completing.
  - Duplicates (Box 49-50)